so something that I think a lot of
people who are coming to um try to see
and understand the
dhama there are a few avenues that we
can take towards the Brahma
viharas there's kind of the Common View
that this is a simple practice that
anybody can just do you can just tell
somebody take somebody off the street
and say oh go sit in your room think of
like a cute kitty cat and kind of that
energy that you feel that like that love
you feel if you can direct that to
everybody even your enemies then you're
you're cultivating the Brahma
viharas um and there's also so you can
kind of take that Avenue if this is easy
anybody can do it or you can kind of say
these are really
esoteric mystical
States um I'm not going to really worry
about this at all until you know later
once I kind of have gotten all this
other stuff out of the way um and almost
putting it on a pedestal that's too high
so I guess my question is what is a
practical way of approaching the topic
of the brah of vioro that is not putting
it on a pedestal that's too high or kind
of
um hopefully kind of pulling it down to
say oh well yeah this is easy I could do
this
easily well the the first thing
that essentially any discussion should
begin with is the point that um you
don't get the right view you don't
achieve stream entry by um doing some
practice that then gives you a result
you reach stre entry by understanding
how to do any practice that the Buddha
taught because as he said um all all
wholesome things converge in the four
noble truths so you need to have that sense of
truths so you need to have that sense of
what the problem is in order to develop
these practices that are treatments for
the problem and so that would undercut that
problem and so that would undercut that
sense of like okay I'll just do this and
then I'll reach that that result because
you be assuming that you're already
doing it properly and that's really the
problem where is it it should be more of
a sense of whether it's Brahma viharas
or anything
else understanding how to do this is
stream entry understanding the path to
Liberation from suffering understanding
right mindfulness understanding right
composure understanding right effort
understanding wholesome and un wholesome
these things are stre entry so that
should be the goal now
um why then would
um what would be the problem with what
you said would be the normal way of
approaching that though like just
thinking of it as a fabrication of of
beautiful pleasant
thoughts well there's no discernment you
just kind of start with the Assumption I
already know what this is so H but know
the sermon to what well no kind of
clarification of your own views no
clarification of
the like kind of what you're bringing to
the practice so to speak and I mean if
you have faith in what the Buddha says
then what he says is the problem has to
do with these things that you're
bringing that are not being questioned
right so so in that case what would be
the assumption that you would be
bringing to the table when you're doing
these
practices I guess I would think that
there could be a few different
assumptions or maybe it's different ways
of kind of explaining the same thing but
um what comes to mind for me is that you
you think you know what needs to be kind
of developed or abandoned MH so you
think that um
oh the point of meta for example is I
need to stop being bothered by this uh
you know just Mouse that's squeaking um
or it needs to stop being unpleasant for
example so I'm going to like cultivat
that like when I hear this mouse
squeaking or when somebody like breaks
down my door and steals all my things
I'll just like be like wow I love you
man so what would
be how how would you phrase that in
terms of like why is that not in line
with the path let's say because you you
can say that but but um it might not be
necessarily obvious to people why that's
why that's the problem well it means you
assume feeling is the
problem
um give kind of a robotic
answer which
means that you're not seeing craving is
the problem so as I just mentioned
before the four noble truths are where
all whome things
converge this is kind of why you can say
the right things and it doesn't
necessarily mean that
you've kind of it doesn't mean that
you've understood it in that kind of
direct sense like I can sit here and say
well that way that you know that means
you assume that craving that feeling is
the problem which means you're
overlooking craving but that doesn't
mean that when it comes down to it I am
necessarily going to like align that
idea with what's happening yeah yeah so
how so how can you prepare so so what is
the best way to prepare yourself for
situations when you do find
intense mind arising due to
circumstances like do you need to wait
for that to happen and then recollect
these instructions
or or you can well
the problem with waiting is you kind of
assume it doesn't apply to you right now
yeah so so even right now when the mind
is not angry not overcome by ill will
and and no external circumstances are
bothering it
particularly what would the right
practice of of meta in this case then
consist
of just to challenge the idea that you
can only practice this when actually
somebody is being angry with you oh and
then right because that can be a view
that that people have like I I need to
wait to be in that situation then I can
apply this instruction that I have
received you just put it on the Shelf
somewhere and you just take it but
that's not mind development
then so you're on your own in your cie
there's not even anyone
there can you then still practice meta I guess
there I guess there would have to be
kind of on some level something that is
um like even if you are
content um and you say well there's
nothing that I'm kind of discontented
about to practice meta with
um so long as you're not free from
suffering there is going to be on some
level a something that can be taken as
discontent and this might be wrong I'm
not I'm not entirely sure but you
um like in that case kind of your well
it might might be the case that like you
know I'm wanting to practice meta but
there's nothing for me to like practice
it with regard to it's like well that
kind of
frustration which is a bit more subtle
than like we're used to kind of being
angry about like somebody like more
coarse things kind of that can kind of
fly under the radar but but can you just
start with that subtle
level no not not unless you kind of have
a um a habit in place
of yeah doing this with regard to the
more coarse thing so so what would be
the more coarse things that you do
practice metha with even though they're
not necessarily other people well I
guess that kind of leads me to say that
practice keeping the precepts could be
like or that
is developing that yeah well keeping the
precepts with the at the same time um
understanding that um like you said
you're you don't want to just
uh do it with a mindset of discontent so
you want to reach a point where keeping
the precepts while keeping the precept
your mind is content and then that's
another confusion that that people would
think it's like only about people but
really um the principle of ill will is
just in regard to how you feel it's just
a resistance to how you feel so other
people and situations might act as a
trigger for that but that tendency is
there in relation to anything that you
feel and so that's why if you train
yourself for example to put up with the
discomfort of which is where you have to
start always the Buddha said you train
yourself in these things first and then
you begin these mental cultivation
practices with uh virtue like there
isn't any fundamental difference between
that displeasure that you experience
when you stop giving into desires and
the displeasure that you feel when
somebody upsets you or something like
that it's exactly if you train yourself
in regard to one you'll be training
yourself in regard to the other so
that's why um if somebody is you can
actually tell like just practice those a
or something for 6 months and you will
see um even if you haven't made like
great effort to to develop wisdom you
will see that you'll be less more
difficult to to make you angry than it
was before and so because another issue
with this view of of just uh fabricating
these these you
know like corny thoughts as a as a
practice is that you don't realize
actually the reason why you have ill
the reason why you have ill
will like would you be able to have ill
will or get angry or or get annoyed if
you don't have
attachments that's why like you can be
doing all of
this spending eight hours a day
practicing metha but throughout your day
you keep shoving fuel into that fire of
Desire the liability to to will is being
fed because like okay I have all these
possessions I have all these um you know
friends family uh Pleasures that I
depend on and as soon as anybody or
anything um brings those things under
threat I will be liable immediately the
the ill will will be there and that is
actually the root of ill will so I mean
they they're like two sides of the same
coin so that's that's why even if you
never make effort to practice meta but
you free yourself from any dependence on
any pleasure any attachment you will
have mind of meta yeah because there
would be less or nothing at all for you
to defense B yeah and then and then you
might not necessarily see because then
if you confuse that meta with like the
specific uh positive thinking or
whatever then you might not see that
actually that's a byproduct of the mind
of meta that's not even it's not even
necessarily um what what defines it like like
um what what defines it like like
something doesn't need to be smoking in
order to be
hot so it's more of a side effect mhm
and so it's
uh then you might see somebody who is
for example in ARA like free from
suffering like the Buddha himself
actually and uh you see in the suta is
like he never
smiled and that would be
that would be something that you know
people would confuse meta with that
attitude of like being super kind of
externally U with that overly friendly
behavior and and and um that's not what
it is because he himself who he said he
he has the highest meta the highest
compassion the the highest uh Equanimity
of all beings and yet I mean you even
read how he would sometimes rebuke and
admonish monks and and things like that
yeah uh and
uh that's that's that shows that it's
actually byproduct of having cultivated
the mind of meta so all those thoughts
that you see for example in the meta
suta like may all beings be happy U may
they be free from illness may may they
be um free from enmity and and not um
have conflict with each other and what
not those thoughts would
arise by themselves for somebody who has
freed themselves from that liability to
ill will so in other words if you heat
up the thing it's going to start smoking
but you don't like try to create the
smoke directly or or another example
would be you know how how some people
like that uh there's this idea that you
fake it till you make it so for example
you might see somebody who has a very
confident demeanor like a millionaire or
something who goes around you know with
a very proud and and and confident
expression and just try to copy his
mannerisms without actually having all
the things that give him that confidence
and then that's going to be like a
facade it's going to it's going to crack
easily basically it's Hollow whereas if
you actually develop yourself to gain
those things that brought him that
confidence you will have it truly and
you will not need to even think about
faking it like sometimes like you would
even think about
how I move my hands or what I do it's
just um it would be a natural byproduct
yeah and what is it according to the dad
that brings
confidence the
RW what kind of knowing
what to do essentially yeah nobody are
confident but also there's another
factor which is which is described as
that which which makes people confident
even before the Right View authenticity more
specifically yeah it says virtue virtue
is that which brings um uh confidence
some when somebody is virtuous and then
they make an offering even to Great
beings they will do so respectfully
confidently um um because they they have
a already
um to some degree that sense of
blamelessness they're not divided
against themselves because they have
cleared all that up on account of virion
yeah and and that's how you would
actually get to it like by really so to
speak getting your hands dirty and and
not acting out of anger in those
situations that incite anger whether
through body speech or even eventually
mind that's how you would reach that
confidence that no like it's not that I
the ill will arises because of this sort
of quick moment that I didn't catch and
I didn't start the practice soon enough
and it got out of hand you would realize
that that's on account of your own
choices this was happening and that
builds confidence because now you know
that that will not come back by itself
yeah like it it's like you open the door
and it comes in and uh you were doubtful
and not confident before because you
didn't see that Gateway where you know
the ill will you were you were allowing
it in and so that's why the
the the the whole point is you need to
then not see this this U this pleasure
that comes up when people annoy you when
people um do things that that that you
don't like uh you need to see that as
like uh you need to see that as
um as what your practice happens in
relation to in other words the
displeasure is not the problem that's
that's the whole point of the Four Noble
Truths feeling is not the issue craving
is the issue and craving is most acutely
reflected by your actions so you start
from you will not be able to purify your
mental actions until you purify your
bodily actions uh but that's how you
would see that principle like okay I I
cannot do anything about um the way this
person makes me feel but I certainly
have 100% say on my actions on what I do
and eventually you would see that on the
mental level it's the same principle
it's not that the mental part happens
happens suddenly and uh and like I said
yeah then at some points if you really
develop that and you get to the root of
it which is that aversion towards that
displeasure you you work on that level
instead of how do I make this pleasure
go away so that I have piece kind of
like covering up the liability then you
would even the the the thing would switch and
even the the the thing would switch and
then you would start having these
genuine thoughts of wishing Goodwill but
as a again as a byproduct of the mental
state that you have cultivated yeah so
you're not standing in front of the
mirror repeating certain thoughts you
know male beings this or that and and
when it says like then you you um spread
as this with Define you pervade the
whole world the first quarter second
quarter north south east west with that
attitude it's it's exactly when you have
already developed it when you when your
mind has that strength to be able to put
up with any displeasure that comes up
without drifting into ill will then you
can um yeah then you can start uh
finding points or or aspects of your
experience of your life where maybe you
would be liable to this ill will and by
recollecting that same attitude in that
direction or or bringing that attitude
in that same direction you
pervade yeah that's actually a good
point so it might be U helpful to draw a
parallel here between the practice of
sense restraint and what we're now
talking in terms of the B viar right
when you're on your own in your CI there
might not be anything uh sensual going
on you're in the forest there no people
there and so on but that doesn't mean
that you've abandoned sensuality then
the question is am I still liable then I
find myself in certain situations to to
to Resort back to sensuality that's the
whole practice of contemplating the
danger in sensuality now it seems to me
it's exactly the same with these har
there might not be other people but you
are contemplating the danger of acting
out of ill will that's that's that's
because you have a choice yeah that's
just parallel it it's exactly the it's
exactly the same attitude and and this
this is best developed when you are
alone with your own mind because as you
just described fundamentally it is your
relationship to your own mind so to
speak yeah yeah and um and the bud even
said you would be able to practice these
things when you're already able to put
up with agreeable and disagreeable
things without your mind being perturbed
because it's on that basis that you
cultivate meta it's on the basis of okay
I I still have that kind of my mind
would uh go into a will if I let it but
I have developed myself through virtue
and restraint to the point where okay
the possibility is there but I don't
choose it only when you have reached
that point and you don't need to be
antido things and thinking the opposite
and uh putting a veil over the problem
so as to feel better temporarily when
you can actually as the Buddha even said
his mind is not not overcome by Arisen
UNH wholesome States that's in gut
nikaya 863 and then he says then he can
practice meta so would you say that that's
meta so would you say that that's
actually how you fake it until you make
it kind of taking the The Stance of like
in my experience I mean unless you're
doing something blatantly un wholesome
like breaking a precept at that point
but otherwise kind of starting with the
like there's nothing in my experience
that is kind of qualitatively different
from that of an
Arun so you kind of fake it in that
internal sense of like well if there is
this kind of arisen pressure or
unpleasant feeling kind of
acting in such a way that it's not um
kind of acting as if it's not uh but how
do you know that in your experience
there's nothing different from
AR well isn't that kind of the um the
um the
um the principle of
like if you think there's something you
need to get rid of or kind of
find then you're overlooking kind of the
work that can be done which is the
attitude towards what is in other words
a feeling you you could look at it from
the point of view that a feeling is a
feeling and then the point will always
the problem will always come from your
attitude towards it um and again that's
something you can have that idea but um
unless you're assult Upon A yet that
distinction between feeling and the
attitude towards it has not been
clarified enough that's what that's
that's where the work lies and so then
um only then would you be able to
develop through any of these practices
you would take that same principle
because whether it's meta whether it's
auba whether it's anything else that the
Buddha taught it's the same principle of
feeling is there and you're you see that
that's not the problem H but you see
that you have that option to have a
certain context a certain attitude a
certain disposition or way of relating
to it and then you clearly see that
distinction and then you can just do one
of these practices and that will
establish you in non-
craving um
so but as as you said it's
um yeah you can start from that point of
view saying okay yeah I'm not doing
anything UNH wholesome I'm not I'm I'm
I'm I'm restraining myself so now the
point here is not like how do I
make this go away in that assumed sense
of antido and and replacing it's more
like how do I learn not to be moved by
this and that's
when that's when eventually you could
get to that genuine um mind of of that's
incapable of giving rise to the will
because the Buddha in fact said uh if
somebody thinks I have developed meta
but my mind is still uh taken by a will
he he should be told don't misrepresent
Buddha because he wouldn't say that and
um and you know people might not realize
that no matter how proficient you become
at this practice of trying to think the
opposite and and and fabricating nice
thoughts even if you're
99.99999% sure that it's going to work
it still requires chance cuz you're
basically like you you don't see the mind you
like you you don't see the mind you
don't understand how this works you just
kind of do it and it happens to work
statistically speaking but you don't see
exactly for yourself what is the ill
will you just took that instruction of
like you said visualize this visualize
that and yes it works but you don't see
what ill will is which means there will
be times and situations where it's going
to get out of hand eventually uh it's
going to have to happen and um you will
be liable to will but if you have
understood what meta is it's not a
matter of chance anymore it's not a
matter if I just do this and sometimes
it works you see exactly what o will is
and you see that it cannot happen by
accident well then it's really theop you
don't even need to do anything anymore
yeah exactly your mind is incapable of
falling back on onto these previous
unome States yeah so then that's when
you would have that certainty of not
like I became so proficient at this and
I developed the skill of meta it's like
no this this thing will not come back
even if I just relax for the rest of my
life it will not come back and
um that's a that's a huge distinction
cuz if you're not honest with yourself
you might Overlook that that still your
success depends on on kind of like
circumstantially you pressing these
buttons and it happens to work
mhm and I think it's like just what kind
of what I get from what you say is that
just like switching like kind of our
attitude when we come to the sutas I can
read the sentence like oh may all being
be free from enmity and say oh yeah I
know what does it mean and I kind of
repeat that sentence over and over again
but like what you kind of invite us to
do more it will be like to take like may
all beings be free from enmity did I
actually understand what enmity means in
that sentence because like I cannot
reach to someone something that I don't
understand what kind of city like yeah
you you that's another thing you you
could have these flowery thoughts of of
them you know wishing for people to to
not experience unpleasant
situations because you still for
yourself confused unpleasant situations
with suffering so um you might have like
that's when like the engaged meta or
whatever then becomes like practice of
all I need to protect people from go out
of my way to protect people from
experiencing unpleasant circumstances
it's not bad in itself but if you
confuse that with oh I'm helping prevent
suffering that's like you you confuse
the fact that that even for yourself
unpleasant feeling is not suffering so
the only way that actually you can
diminish people's suffering is by
teaching them that unpleasant feeling is
not suffering other were teaching them
the for noal truth yeah if they want to
understand yeah that's the whole
principle of the K Maita right ma is the
same root as the as The Meta like a good
friend is not somebody as you just
described who protects you from un CC
and so but who actually shows how you
can become independent in the midst of
adversity in independent of that you
know how to not suffer in the midst of
suffering basically and that view can
kind of justify a lot of blatantly and
wholesome things in the name of
protection Well Company delighting in
company which the Buddha said if you
Delight in company you actually won't be
able to get the right view he said that
explicitly because you won't be able to
understand the signs of your own mind
and somebody who doesn't see the signs
of your of their own mind as it said as
I wrote about it in that essay it's like
that's how exactly how you would be able
to see what craving is what a will is
for example uh by recognizing no it's
that mental kind of background choice I
make when this feeling is present that
is that is the will and then whether I
tell myself that oh this person is
actually not so bad he's doing this
because his his upbringing was was very
difficult or something and he
experienced trouble as a child all of
that is secondary to the point of like
like if you find out that actually
that's not true he didn't have a bad
upbringing he's just a total
because the Buddha said there are
foolish people in the world there are
people who are Beyond repair he said
that and
um then like your meta doesn't work
anymore if it depends on convincing
yourself that the person is good but no
this is doesn't matter how uh blatantly
foolish somebody is and and like he like
the said they're literally sawing your
limbs off uh you still wouldn't have
that internal attitude of um wishing
them harm you doesn't mean you would
just sit there and allow them to kill
you but uh you wouldn't be like wishing
to take revenge or something like that
yeah so the usual psychologizing finding
reasons why all the people behave in a
certain way right which often then you
know going back into the past and and so
on none of that has got anything to do
with the actual practice of meta
whatsoever yeah that's just that whole
domain is just like
um it's finding roundabout ways to make
this feeling not be what it is because
you think that's what the problem is and
you don't see that the way you again
craving in regard to the way you feel is
what the problem is yeah and I just like
listening to you I was just like
thinking that this whole practice is
actually kind of Bas also
to not take responsibility for judgment
oh I should not judge everyone is good I
wish them well everyone like may all of
them be happy and things like that so
that I don't judge them so I don't judge
see if I don't judge other I start to
not judge myself and I feel not
responsible for like kind of my action
and my kind of craving in regard to kind
of my feeling and things like that it
feels like this kind of practice is just
based upon like the the kind of
assumptions like judgments is a kind of
bad thing the bad things but like
judgments is not optional so yeah and
and The Bu said uh the second
Enlightenment factor is is Judgment
that but Judgment of whome and un
wholesome so um and he also said you
should be able to tell a fool from a
wise person I you cannot fundamentally
not judge that's that's actually that's
that's another thing but that would be
more philosophical and then then U
another thing like oh having meta toward
yourself people would think like oh I
shouldn't be too restrained or I I I
should like take it easy not not go too
hard in the practice MD but see that's
that's again confusing like oh I
shouldn't put myself through a pleasant
situation because I think that's what
suffering is but if you had met that for
yourself you would see no no actually um
what's in my best interest is to to
understand that this displeasure that
I'm experiencing on account of this
practice is not the problem and what's
in my best interest is to actually
restrain myself and tame this mind so
that it won't be liable to not just like
extending this principle of this
displeasure and I see that this exactly
this which causes all the problems not
only for myself but for other people
like when when other people do something
to you and you get angry and you end up
acting out again it's not because of
them it's because of the way you are
feeling right now which is the same as
the way you are feeling when you're
being restrained and it's difficult it's
that same internal resistance you have
toward your own mind is what gets you to
act out of those things so if you cannot
tolerate that pressure of sense
Restraint of virtue of celibacy it's
impossible that you'll be able to
tolerate every circumstance of somebody
making you angry and making you upset
because another thing is that you know
we are quite proliferated nowadays in in
terms of how much we can prevent people
from doing things that we don't like
like you know there's all these um laws
and and rules and and things that people
now don't do things not because
internally they are virtuous but because
the government will punish them if they
do them it's much more difficult to get
away with things you yeah so back in the
day you know people might be doing
things that that nowadays they they
might go to prison for and because of
that you know people don't experience a
lot of the time you can go throughout
your life
uh experiencing only very minor upsets
and then this this I mean for you it
might feel like a huge deal but in like
the wide scope of things is actually
very minor and and then for you like you
you're dealing with these management
practices of fabricating good thoughts
and stuff it's going to work but like
you know dealing with I don't
know extremely unfair circumstances like
actually this mother this this mother of
a of this this young man in the suas who
who was taken prisoner and and killed
unfairly by the king and U that's a sort
of thing that would happen in those days
and she was an anagami in other words
she had developed that mind of meta and
it said throughout that whole process
that she saw her son being taken away
and prison and killed uh she didn't like
her mind didn't move she was not
perturbed and now like yeah but if you
were to say that now out loud you end up
in a psychic W yeah and and now imagine
like I don't think there unless you're
extremely uh self- dishonest I don't
think somebody who who who even the most
success successful person with these
meta management sort of fabrication
techniques of Imagine The as you said
like the cute cat or something in your
head and extend that attitude that's not
going to work when your son gets killed
no so
um but if if you have develop yourself
in virtue and and and and all that you
can see that's already much closer to
that direction of of being not liable to
a will
anymore what you were saying about the
um kind of blaming this on others a
little bit earlier um that's something
that's amp Amplified by Solitude because
if you're annoyed at people and say
you're kind of stuck with those people
for say you're on like a long TR brain
you're and like these people are
annoying you like unless you're really
developed already like so long as
they're kind of right there you're going
to be kind of blaming them for it let
say something happens you're annoyed
with somebody and then you're alone in
your room for the rest of the day and
that's still kind
of that becomes more obvious like okay
it's me doing this like I've been alone
for 12 hours and here I am still kind of
like it's not it's not obvious and
that's why like this Solitude and stuff
it's not like one evening I do it no
it's a training for a prolonged period
of time and then you're kind of putting
yourself in the situation where you will
be able to discern it if you try and
then um that's exactly why it says you
won't be able to see your signs of your
mind in other words those internal
choices you're making you won't be able
to see that unless you uh you train
yourself in
solitude so
and and obviously as well uh you need to
be alone to practice mea as you just
said you cannot be like like like I
practice like I mentioned before
engaging with people trying to practice
Like Loving actions and and kind actions
and stuff helping people um and and
expecting to practice mea because that's
not what it's about like it might make
you feel good but again it would be in
that temporary management sense and and
you're not actually Discerning these uh
intentions of a will that you are liable
to um externally and you also want to
look at it in a certain way where like
you know okay what I think meta is I've
been developing it towards this person
in these external ways of either through
actions like helping them out and again
not that that's bad but the wrong view
is thinking that that is where the
practice happens uh you know helping
them out and and using super gentle kind
speech and and with my mind as well
thinking these Loving Thoughts and
now if somebody comes and harms that
person would I have a will towards the
person who like is that actually
increasing my liability to be angry with
the person who does something to them
yeah because you have might of in you're
building up attachment yeah exactly so
you're building up selectiveness and uh
and that's quite the opposite of the
mind of meta which is as as the
description says boundless unlimited and
it's not fixed upon anything yeah so
it's it's uh that's why it's closer
actually to equinity which is why it
would naturally culminate in equinity
which is the fourth Brahma bhara which
is the highest yeah uh whereas I think
most people would have that background
assumption that that one's kind of
like not as good because it's kind of
cold and harsh to be aanus but no the
Buddha is actually saying this is the
best one this is the best of all So Meta
would naturally culminate in that
because it's already closer to that than
your normal state of like random person
just having nice
thoughts uh it it would take you beyond
sensuality as well because it's is um as
I said before it's that same attitude of
resisting displeasure well that same
displeasure that you get for example
when you don't give your senses what
they want that that is the same annoyance and
want that that is the same annoyance and
and and discomfort in its nature that
you experience when people do bad things
to you so if you overcome one liability
that aversion um towards your own
feelings you will overcome sensuality as
well and the opposite applies if you
have no attachments if you have no
desires if you have no Pleasures that
you depend on you cannot hate anyone
because there's nothing for you there's
nothing that you own that could be
compromised I think that even this one
Su in MA where it says
that sensuality is really the
origin of all hatred and ill will and
then it goes step by step and then it
says all the way to the point of taking
uptick and fighting and but so in our
times that's war and and so so um uh
that's fascinating like um so if you
like even from a social perspective if
you don't want to have war in a country
or in a certain region that's never
going to become
established as as long as people people
there do not see the value in Restraint
so if you have a society that tends
towards the hedonistic side of the
spectrum that values come for an instant
Cal yeah that is just sewing the seeds
for future conflict and so that is also
a way of seeing the danger in sensuality
and it's important it seems to me to not
think like black and white like oh the B
of peace is not the absence of
War it's also not not like that uh this
is why the Buddha often talks about you
know it is why we talk about liability
to things so so you cannot just say
something doesn't seem to be happening
externally therefore I'm at peace now
because circumstances change and then
the whole thing still explodes he he
talked about this with the with the five
lower feds in maim 64 he mentioned like
somebody might think that the five lower
feds is just these specific
manifestations of these things and then
he said well if that's the case then a
newborn baby is free from these things
because he doesn't know what Identity or
or personality view is he doesn't know
what virtue and and duty is he doesn't
know what doubt is he he he he doesn't
even know what sensual Pleasures are or
what what beings are so how could he
have ill will towards them yeah that's
right and he said but no it's the
underlying tendency which would be on the level of
tendency which would be on the level of
that feeling like when he when he
feels displeasure his mind pulls back
from it when he feels pleasure his mind
inclines towards it and that is the
basis for
everything and that's where that
liability is so if and and you really
want to start seeing it on that General
level not thinking that like I need to
develop myself in relation to when this
situation happens and this situation
happens and it's kind of like this um
almost like a cognitive what's it called
cognitive behavioral therapy or
something like that no no it's the
fundamental nature of feeling you that
that's the root of everything your
attitude towards that
yeah so can we then also say that when
that when somebody is practicing sense
restraints properly they are already
indirectly moving towards B yaras yeah
yeah it's it is not that that we're now
talking about something separate that
you do on the side no it's just it's
that same principle yeah um so that seem
because sometimes as you said in the
beginning like there might be sort of
mystical esoteric ideas from this and
that and then you know might become a
bit lofty and and and and not the right
idea but you can just ground yourself in
but you can just ground yourself in
precisely understanding one's
relationship to feeling and just you
know understand the virtue and the Sens
St and and whether you like it or not
you you will factually as you said be
less liable to act out of ill will
because you you you begin to see that in
your own experience so you will be
moving in in that direction it cannot
not go there the same with Janna when
the Buddha said um if somebody
practices uh basically any type anything
any any wholesome thing that's rooted in
that discernment of craving even for a
finger snap he it says he's not empty
he's not devoid of J so even if you're
not aiming towards that the point is the
mind is being tamed and that's what what
is the the root of all these these uh
wholesome States that's why he compared
it to this um like a bowl that when you
fill it with water whichever direction
you tilt it it can go in that like the
water will flow in that direction so you
fill that bowl up which is the gradual
training the sensory trained virtue not
acting out of these UNH wholesome
intentions and then whether you're
tilted in the direction of raras janas
uh immaterial attainments um casinas
whatever whatever takes your fancy it
will go in that direction because all of
it revolves around that principle of of
um feeling and craving
if it doesn't revolve around that then
it's not part of the Buddhist teaching
and he wouldn't have mentioned it that's
why he said he teaches only one thing
suffering and freedom from suffering
which is uh abandoning of craving